<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached in Saint Maries Church in Oxford March 26. 1612. at the funerall of Thomas Holland, Doctor of the Chaire in Divinitie, and Rector of the Exceter College, by Richard Kilbie Doctor of Divinity, Rector of Lincolne College</title>
            <author>Kilbye, Richard, 1560 or 61-1620.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04823</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14957</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107985</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843676</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843676</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8424</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04823)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8424)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 760:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached in Saint Maries Church in Oxford March 26. 1612. at the funerall of Thomas Holland, Doctor of the Chaire in Divinitie, and Rector of the Exceter College, by Richard Kilbie Doctor of Divinity, Rector of Lincolne College</title>
                  <author>Kilbye, Richard, 1560 or 61-1620.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Joseph Barnes, and are to be sold by Iohn Barnes dwelling neere Holborne Conduit [, London],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Holland, Thomas, 1539-1612 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8424:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8424:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED IN SAINT MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIES CHVRCH IN OXFORD March 26. 1612. at the funerall of THOMAS HOLLAND, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of the Chaire in Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and Rector of Exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter College, BY RICHARD KILBIE <hi>Doctor of Divinity, Rector of Lincolne College.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <head>AC: OX</head>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at Oxford by Joſeph Barnes, and are to be ſold by Iohn Barnes dwelling neere Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne Conduit. 1613.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:8424:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:8424:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1. COR. 15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>55</bibl> O death where is thy ſting? O graue, where is thy victory?</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>56</bibl> The ſting of death is ſinne: and the ſtrength of ſinne is the law.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>57</bibl> But thankes be vnto God, which hath giuen vs victory through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe parcels of holy Scripture na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally divide and branch them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues into theſe foure head-ſtreams.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 The ioyfull <hi>Exultation</hi> and Triumphant inſultation of all the godly, in the perſon of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paule, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Death</hi> and the <hi>Graue [O death, where is thy ſting? O graue where is thy victory?]</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 The originall <hi>Cauſe</hi> of <hi>Death;</hi> which is <hi>ſinne. [The ſting of death is ſinne.]</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 The <hi>Power</hi> and life (as it were) of <hi>Sinne;</hi> which is the <hi>Law [The ſtrength of ſinne is the law.]</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4 And laſt, The <hi>Victory</hi> and conqueſt of Chriſtians in their head and Captaine Chriſt Ieſus over <hi>Sinne,</hi> and <hi>Death [Thankes bee vnto God, which hath given vs victory through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.]</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Of all theſe by Gods gracious aſſiſtance &amp;c. But firſt of the cauſe of Death, which is Sinne, and ſo of the reſt;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:8424:3"/>
and in the laſt place of the triumphant Inſultation over death, which will beſt befit the preſent occaſion.</p>
            <p>It was the errour, or hereſie rather, of the Pelagians (as S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> 
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> writeth) that whether <hi>Adam</hi> had ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned or no,<note place="margin">Auguſtin. lib. 1. Hypognoſt contra Art. 1.</note> yet hee ſhould ſurely haue dyed; becauſe God had created him mortall, and was the author of death as well as of life: ſo that <hi>Adam</hi> was the immediate ſubiect both of life and death in Gods firſt intention, and inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mankind. Whereas the truth is, that man before his fall was neither mortall nor immortall <hi>(Neceſsitate)</hi> by any neceſſity of creation and inſtitution from God:<note place="margin">Hugo de S<hi rend="sup">to</hi> Victore de ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentis le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis natur. &amp; ſcript. in. dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log.</note> and yet hee was both mortall and immortall <hi>(Poteſtate,)</hi> by his owne power; becauſe then indeed life and death were both in his power. For although, in regard of the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry principles whereof man conſiſted, he had in himſelfe a naturall propenſion to corruption; inaſmuch as contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieties both in bodies naturall &amp; politique, alwaies breed deſtruction of thoſe bodies: yet God in the firſt creation had given that ſpeciall and celeſtiall power &amp; vertue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſoule, that it was ever able to haue preſerued the body from ſickneſſe, and from death, &amp; to haue perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated the ſame throughout all generations. So that the God of <hi>Nature</hi> in the beginning never <hi>intended</hi> that <hi>Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> of Death, as the Pelagians and Celeſtians did errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly conceiue but when the ſoule by her divorce and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration from God through ſinne loſt her life, both <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue,</hi> which ſhe received from God, and <hi>Actiue</hi> which ſhe infuſed to the body, then the ſoule loſt all power and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of perpetuating the life of the body. For what is more iuſt then the law of Retaliation with God, even to puniſh like with like? and therefore (as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith)
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:8424:3"/>
               <hi>Anima volens perdidit vivere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard. in ſerm. ad mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes Templi. Cap. 11.</note> 
               <hi>nolens ergo perdat &amp; vivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficare,</hi> The ſoule of her own accord loſt the life which ſhe had in God; and therefore now will ſhee, nill ſhee, ſhee muſt looſe the life, which ſhe giues vnto the body. And ſo indeed man is now become mortall by neceſſitie; partly, by the fraile condition of the body,<note place="margin">Th. Aquin. in lib. 3. ſentent. diſtinct. 16. artic. 1</note> 
               <hi>vt à cauſa diſponente</hi> as the diſpoſing cauſe (as the Schoolemen ſpeake) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies tending to corruption: but eſpecially by ſinne, <hi>vt à cauſa removente prohibens,</hi> which did remoue the originall iuſtice of the ſoule, which was the obſtacle and barre of death;<note place="margin">Math. 7.13.</note> and ſo let open the doore &amp; <hi>wide gate to hell</hi> &amp; <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</hi> Wherefore God is not the cauſe of Death,<note place="margin">Sap. 1.13.</note> 
               <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us enim mortem non fecit, God made not death,</hi> but <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,</hi> by ſuggeſtion; and <hi>Adam,</hi> by ſinfull action: the one moving to ſinne, the other committing ſinne. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as the theefe or malefactour is the author of his owne death, and the iuſt Iudge no cauſe thereof; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit he pronounce the ſentence of death againſt him: In like manner, ſinnefull man is the cauſe of his owne death both of body and ſoule, and God is but the iuſt Iudge to pronounce the ſentence of death, <hi>Morte morieris;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 2.17.</note> Thou haſt ſinned, and therefore <hi>thou ſhalt ſurely die.</hi> For ſinne is indeed that ſting of the ſerpent, that ſtingeth ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to death:<note place="margin">Auguſtin. lib. 1. Hypogu.</note> it is not the biting of the ſerpent only, as <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riues the Latine word <hi>Mors à morſu ſerpentis,</hi> as if death had its name of the biting of the ſerpent; but it is more, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the ſting of the ſerpent, becauſe as the poiſon of the ſerpent is collected and vnited in a ſmal ſting, as the fitteſt inſtrument of deadly poiſon: ſo al the venome &amp; poiſon of Death is in the ſting of ſinne. For ſinne is the <hi>Father</hi> of Death, <hi>By one man ſinne entred into the world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5.12.</note> 
               <hi>and death by
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:8424:4"/>
ſin:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 1.15.</note> and it is the <hi>Mother</hi> of Death, <hi>When luſt hath conceived, it bringeth forth ſin, and ſin bringeth forth death.</hi> Let none then make God the author of death, becauſe by his iuſt ſentence he condemneth man to die for ſinnes ſake, &amp; the treſpaſſing of his law, as the Iudge the malefactour for offending againſt the lawes of God and man: Neither let any thinke Sathan the author of death or of puniſhments <hi>Propriâ poteſtate,</hi> as by his owne power; <hi>ſed permiſsione di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinâ &amp; propria ſuggeſtione,</hi> but as of Gods permiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; of his own ſuggeſtion: And let every one of vs ſay vnto ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 12.7.</note> as <hi>Nathan</hi> ſaid to <hi>David, Thou art the man,</hi> Thou art the cauſe of thine owne death. For it is ſinne as a viper in the bowels of man, which eateth out the bowels of man; it is the canker of ſinne in the heart of man, that devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the heart of man:<note place="margin">Hos. 13.8.</note> and as God ſaid to Iſraël, <hi>Perditio tua ex te ô Iſraël, O Iſraël thy deſtruction commeth of thy ſelfe;</hi> the like may God ſay to every man, O ſinneful man, thy death and thy deſtruction commeth of thy ſelfe. For as the heathen Oratour ſaide of the priviledge of a Citizen of Rome,<note place="margin">Cic. prodomo ſuâ ad Pontif</note> 
               <hi>Nemo Civis Romanus aut libertatem aut civitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amittere poteſt niſi ipſe author factus ſit,</hi> No citize<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Rome could haue his freedome taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, or looſe the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges and immunities of his City, except himſelfe was the authour thereof: the ſame may truely bee ſpoken of the excellent Priviledges &amp; Prerogatiues of Paradiſe, the City of God, wherein <hi>Adam</hi> was firſt enfranchiſed, that none could take away <hi>Adams</hi> freedome from him, or ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh him from that heavenly City, except himſelfe had beene the firſt cauſe thereof, except himſelfe had disfran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſed himſelfe. For it was <hi>Adams</hi> ſin, that brought him death; and the ſtinge of his ſinne hath ſtung all mankinde
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:8424:4"/>
to death: <hi>through the offence of one, death paſſed vpon all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5.12.</note> 
               <hi>for as much as all haue ſinned</hi> in him. <hi>Rom. 5.</hi> Yea the little childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who die ſo ſoone as they are new borne, are ſtung to death through ſin; not becauſe they committed ſin, but becauſe they were conceived in ſin:<note place="margin">Auguſtin Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pognoſt. lib. 5.</note> as <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> doth wel diſtinguiſh their ſin to be <hi>vterinâ conceptione, non per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonali actione,</hi> through their ſinneful conception, and not through any perſonall action. <hi>Parvuli enim non actu,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>ſed ortu ſunt peccatores,</hi> Infants are ſinners, not for any fact,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 51 5.</note> but for birth ſake, they are <hi>conceived in ſin, and borne in ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</hi> For if they had beene free from all originall ſin, as they were from actual ſin, they ſhould not ſo ſoone haue died, becauſe <hi>the wages of ſin is death;</hi> and where is no ſinne,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.23.</note> there is no death; to wit <hi>Neceſsary</hi> and <hi>Poenall.</hi> For albeit Chriſt died, <hi>who did no ſinne,</hi> yet his death was <hi>Voluntary,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.22.</note> 
               <hi>Tradidit in mortem animam ſuam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 53 12. Iohn 10.18.</note> he offered himſelfe of his owne will to die; <hi>he powred out his ſoule vnto death; hee laid downe his life of himſelfe:</hi> But all other men die neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily; <hi>Statutum eſt omnibus ſemel mori,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 9.27.</note> 
               <hi>It is appointed to all men that they ſhould once die;</hi> it was the decree of God for ſinnes ſake that everie man ſhould die, and that decree of God was not, <hi>Reſpectu naturae inſtitutae,</hi> in regard of the firſt created nature of man, <hi>ſed reſpectu naturae deſtitutae,</hi> in reſpect of the depraved and corrupted nature of man through ſinne. Againe, Chriſts death was <hi>Expiatory,</hi> but mans <hi>Poenall:</hi> Chriſts death was not the ſting of ſinne <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiuely,</hi> to be ſtung to death by ſin, as mans was; but it was the ſting of ſinne <hi>Actiuely,</hi> to ſting ſinne to death; for his death was the death of death. Thus then you haue heard the cauſe of death to be ſinne, according to theſe words of my Text [<hi>The ſting of death is ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:8424:5"/>The ſecond thing which I noted is the <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Sinne,</hi> which is the <hi>Law [The ſtrength of ſinne is the law.]</hi> Whereas ſinne in the time of the Law of Nature in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny did ſeeme dead, or at leaſt ſenſeleſſe, and to lie as in a tranſe, ſo that it did not manifeſtly appeare what was ſin, and what was not, the eies of mens minds and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings being darkned and overcaſt with groſſe miſts of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and errour; then the law of <hi>Moſes</hi> brought ſinne to life againe.<note place="margin">Rom. 7 9.</note> 
               <hi>Quando enim venit mandatum, revixit pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum, when the commandement came, ſinne reviued.</hi> The bright ſunſhine of <hi>Moſes</hi> Law made ſinne ſhine cleere in its perfect colours; and then the darkneſſe and confuſion of the differences of ſinnes was taken away, that every one might <hi>runne and read</hi> what ſinne was:<note place="margin">Rom 7.13.</note> 
               <hi>Et ſupra modum peccatum erat peccatum per mandatum, ſinne was growne out of meaſure ſinfull by the commandement.</hi> For the law made the full tide of ſinne; which grew by theſe degrees. Firſt, in his being: for ſinne had his beginning, and being as it were from the Law;<note place="margin">Rom. 4.15.</note> becauſe <hi>where no law is, there is no tranſgreſsion, Rom. 4.</hi> Secondly in the knowledge of ſinne: as <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paule</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.7.</note> 
               <hi>I knewe not ſinne but by the Law; for how ſhould I haue knowne luſt, except the Law had ſaid, Thou ſhalt not luſt?</hi> Wherefore knowledge hoyſſeth vp the waues of ſin: for where the greateſt knowledge is, there the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſinne is, if vertue &amp; godlineſſe be not the handmaids of knowledge, and that it be not ſeaſoned with grace, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as our Saviour ſaith,<note place="margin">Luk. 12 47.</note> 
               <hi>Luk. 12. That man who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his maſters will, and doth it not, ſhall bee beaten with many ſtripes.</hi> And therefore ſaith <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paul, Tribulation &amp; anguiſh, and indignation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom 2 9.</note> 
               <hi>and wrath ſhall bee vpon the ſoule of every man that doth evill, of the Iew firſt, and alſo of the Gentile.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:8424:5"/>
Rom. 2.</hi> Why vpon the Iew firſt, but becauſe hee knewe moſt, and therefore is firſt and moſt puniſhed?<note place="margin">Theophilact. in cap. 2. ad Rom.</note> as <hi>Theophy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lact</hi> on that place ſaith, <hi>Iudaeus plus divinae ſuſceperat diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plinae, vnde erat dignus maiore ſupplicio;</hi> The Iew had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued a greater meaſure of knowledge, and therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth a greater meaſure of puniſhment; becauſe hee knewe the Law of the Lord but did not keepe it. Thirdly, the Law encreaſeth ſinne by forbidding ſin: for the more the Law forbiddeth ſin, the more doth the wicked ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet ſinne. <hi>Ruimus in vetitum,</hi> we runne with all might and main to that which is forbidden vs,<note place="margin">Auguſt. in lib. de ſperitu &amp; litera cap 4.</note> 
               <hi>Quod enim concupiſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur fit iucundius dum vetatur;</hi> The prohibitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of any thing to be done is as ſuger to ſweeten the appetite thereof: as the forbidding of meats many times by the Phyſition needeth no further ſauce to provoke appetite in the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient moſt of all to deſire thoſe meats. And as ſwelling waters, the more they are barred their courſe and flow by flood-gates, and lockes, and wheires, the more they rage and ſwell and overflowe: ſo the more the Law doth ſeem to bolt and barre men from ſinne, and to ſet them their bounds which they ſhould not paſſe, the more is ſinfull mans nature enraged, and the more the ſwelling waues of wickedneſſe do overflowe, and make their full tide. All which commeth to paſſe, not becauſe the law is ſinne, for it is <hi>holy, iuſt, and good:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7.12.</note> but becauſe the Law is as a by-occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and not any iuſt cauſe to increaſe ſinne, and to giue vigour and ſtrength therevnto. For the law is <hi>the ſtrength of ſinne,</hi> not of it ſelfe, but by accident; not directly, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>directly; as appeareth by the three former degrees of <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, knowing,</hi> and <hi>forbidding:</hi> as alſo by the great induſtrie and pollicie of Sathan, who ſeeing God to haue made
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:8424:6"/>
the Law as a barre to keepe men from ſinne, doth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore labour the more to tempt men thereby, and to make the Law as a ſnare to catch men. Wherefore for conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this point, the Law is no more in fault that man groweth more ſinfull thereby, then the ſune in the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is in fault, becauſe ſore and bleare eies become ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer and blind thereby. For as the Phyſition is not to bee blamed, or his phyſicke in fault, becauſe the ſicke patient doth ill apply it, and by his diſtemperature in diet turneth wholſome phiſicke and medicine to the increaſe of his maladie and diſeaſe: In like manner, God the Phyſition of mens ſoules, who gaue his law as a ſoveraigne medicine to preſerue them from ſickneſſe and from ſinne, is not to be blamed, or his law in fault; but ſinfull man, who ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth that ſoveraigne medicine as poyſon vnto his ſoule to increaſe his ſinne. Thus you haue heard how the Law is the ſtrength of ſinne: I come now to the victory &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of Chriſtians in their head and Captaine Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus over ſinne and death [<hi>Thankes bee vnto God, which hath given vs victory tbrough our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When mankind was not able to encounter with Death that great Giant, which did overcome all people by his power, &amp; did trample vpon Kings &amp; Princes, tyrannizing over all at his pleaſure; for indeede death was like that mighty King <hi>Prov. 39.</hi> who had his name of a compound Hebrew word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Alkum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 30 31.</note> and is as much to ſay as <hi>none is able to ſtand or riſe vp againſt him;</hi> like <hi>Ioſua</hi> the Captaine of Iſrael: for as he ſhut Kings &amp; Princes in caues of the earth,<note place="margin">Ios. 10 18.</note> and <hi>roaled great stoces vpon the mouthes of the caues, Ioſ. 10.50.</hi> So death ſhutteth the greateſt Emperors and Kings in caues &amp; in graves, and rowleth great ſtones
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:8424:6"/>
vpon the mouthes thereof, &amp; maketh great tombes ouer them:) I ſay, when mankind was not able to enter liſtes &amp; combate with this potent tyrant, but was forced to yeeld &amp; lie down at his feet: Then <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> that bleſſed ſonne of <hi>God,</hi> and ſonne of <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 17.</note> encountreth like his father <hi>David</hi> with this great <hi>Goliah,</hi> and with a ſtrong maner of fight overcommeth him; not with any inſtrument &amp; wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon of warre, or by fighting, but by dying. Hee ſlayeth death as <hi>David</hi> did <hi>Goliah,</hi> with his owne ſword:<note place="margin">1 Sam. 17.51.</note> He over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth Death with death. <hi>Dum occiditur, occidit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hieronym. lib. 2. Epiſt. 24.</note> as <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Hierome</hi> ſpeaketh; whilſt Sathan and death ſought to kill him, he killeth them both, &amp; maketh his death their death: as it was prophecied of him <hi>Hoſ. 13. O Death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hos. 13.14.</note> 
               <hi>I will be thy death! O graue I will be thy deſtruction! Chriſti enim morte mors mortua eſt;</hi> by Chriſts death, Death died: <hi>Devorauit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hieronym. vbi. ſupra.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; devorata eſt,</hi> it ſought to devoure, and it ſelfe was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured; for whereas it ſought to catch at mans humanity, it was devoured of his deitie. And even therefore, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Apoſtle <hi>Heb. 2.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 2.14.</note> did Chriſt <hi>take fleſh and blood</hi> vpon him, <hi>that</hi> ſo hee might die in his fleſh, and <hi>through death deſtroy Death,</hi> and <hi>him that hath the power of Death, that is, the Devill.</hi> So that Chriſt hath carried away the gates of death,<note place="margin">Iudg. 16.3. Iudg. 16.30.</note> as <hi>Samſon</hi> ſometimes did the gates of <hi>Az<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za:</hi> and hath, like another <hi>Samſon,</hi> by his death ſlaine the great <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> even ſinne and death, and the <hi>Divell.</hi> But ſome peradventure will ſay, how hath Chriſt overcome death how hath his death taken away death; ſeeing death raigneth and ruleth now as much in mens bodies ſince Chriſts death as before, and men die as faſt as before? For anſwer herevnto, you muſt conſider that there bee two manners of death: the one of the body, the other of the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:8424:7"/>
ſoule; the one temporall, the other eternall. Now this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal &amp; ſpiritual death of the ſoule Chriſt hath alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy taken away <hi>In re,</hi> indeed, actually deſtroying that in all the faithfull through remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their ſinnes in his blood: But the temporall death of the body hee hath only taken away <hi>In ſpe,</hi> in hope of the glorious reſurrection of the body at the laſt day, when <hi>death ſhall be ſwallowed vp into victory,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.54. Revel 21.4.</note> and when <hi>there ſhall be no more death.</hi> For this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall death, which is a temporall puniſhment of origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſinne,<note place="margin">Alex. ab Alex. part. 4. qu 8. membr. 8. Artic. 2.</note> Chriſt hath not taken away <hi>Simpliciter,</hi> ſimply and altogither; but <hi>quoad dominium</hi> only, as the Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſpeake: that is, the power and dominion of death is taken away by Chriſt, as appeareth, <hi>Rom. 5.</hi> where it is ſaid that <hi>death raigned from Adam to Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5.14.</note> that is, all the time of the Law incluſiuely;<note place="margin">Pſal. 68.18.</note> eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vntill Chriſt, who by his death hath deſtroyed the kingdome of death, and <hi>hath led capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitie captiue.</hi> And therefore this tyrant Death (whoſe kingdome is alreadie actually deſtroyed, though it ſelfe ſhall not be fully deſtroyed vntill the end of the world, for <hi>the laſt enimie that ſhall be deſtroyed is Death</hi>) I ſay,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.26.</note> this ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Death, being thus depulſed and driven out of his kingdome,<note place="margin">Origen. in c. 5. ad Rom.</note> 
               <hi>No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tam regnare, quàm latrocinari videtur,</hi> doth not ſo much ſeeme to raigne and play the Tyrant, as to play the theefe and murtherer to kill men. And this pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of death Chriſt hath not taken away,<note place="margin">Auguſt. lib 13. de Civit. Dei. Cap. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Ne fides enerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur, quae corporis immortalitatem in ſpe exſpectat, quam in re nondum habet,</hi> as S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> 
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> giueth the reaſon; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the further exerciſe of that part of a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mans faith, whereby he conſtantly beleeues the immortality of the body hereafter, which in this life it cannot haue. Yea Chriſt may bee ſaid in ſome manner already to haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:8424:7"/>
away even the corporall death alſo in the godly, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as much as he hath taken away ſinne which is <hi>the ſting of death,</hi> and as it were the forme and life of death. So that as hony is not truely honie, when it hath loſt its ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; nor Vineger truely vinegar, when it hath loſt its tartneſſe and ſharpneſſe; nor Aloes and Gall truly ſo, when they haue loſt their bitternes: no more is the death of the righteous truely death, hauing loſt its bitterneſſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 69.21.</note> and fearefulneſſe and terrours in the godly. The <hi>gall and vineger,</hi> which Chriſt dranke a little before his death, hath taken away the gall and bitterneſſe of the death of the faithfull, in whom death, hath loſt as the greateſt part of its nature, ſo even the very name of it too, it being in them no more but a <hi>ſleepe,</hi> as it is called in diverſe places of holy Scripture,<note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 4.15.</note> whereof for brevitie ſake I will name but one. <hi>1. Theſſ. 4.</hi> where it is ſaid that <hi>they which liue and are remaining at the comming of the Lord,</hi> in the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>ſhall not prevent thoſe that ſleepe,</hi> that is all thoſe that are dead before. Wherefore to draw towardes a concluſion of this point, it doth appeare how the faithfull are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querours in Chriſt their head and Captaine over ſinne and death; for Chriſts victory is their victory, becauſe all his fighting with ſinne and death and the Divel, the great and capitall enimies of mankind, was only to make men his faithfull members Conquerours: ſo that they may ſay with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paule</hi> in my Text, that God hath given them vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie over ſinne and death through his ſonne Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.<note place="margin">Numb. 21.9.</note> Now is their death become like the <hi>braſen ſerpent</hi> in the wilderneſſe, which had indeed the ſhape and forme of a Serpent, but nothing elſe of a ſerpent, <hi>nec motum, nec morſum, nec venenum;</hi> neither life, nor motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor tongue,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:8424:8"/>
nor ſting, nor poyſon of a ſerpent: In like manner the death of the godly in the wilderneſſe of this world hath the likeneſſe and ſemblance of death; but it hath no ſting, it hath no venome, it hath no poyſon. But, whereas it is to the wicked and vngodly the beginning of ſorrow and everlaſting torments, it is to the godly and righteous the end of ſorrowes, but the beginning of everlaſting ioyes: to the wicked it is the gate of hell; but to the godly the gate to heauen: in a word, to the wicked it is death indeed even death of body and ſoule, but to the righteous rather a life then a death, even the entrance and paſſage to ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life. So that when they lie on their death-beds, and are even at their laſt gaſpe, when they are ready to giue vp the ghoſt, and death ſeemeth to haue gotten the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per hand of them, and brought them almoſt as low as the duſt;<note place="margin">Theod. lib. 1. Eccl. Hiſt. cap 20.</note> yet even then as <hi>Iulian</hi> ſaid to Chriſt <hi>Viciſti Galilaee,</hi> O Galilean, thou haſt overcome me, ſo may death ſay to them <hi>Viciſti Chriſtiane,</hi> O Chriſtian, thou haſt overcome me. No marvaile then if our bleſſed Apoſtle here in my Text, in the perſon of all the godly, burſt forth into that ioyfull <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and triumphant ſong, <hi>[O death, where is thy ſting? O graue where is thy victory?]</hi> which now followeth in the laſt place to be conſidered, containing the ioyfull exultation, and triumphant inſultation of the godly over Death, and Hell, and the Graue.</p>
            <p>The Heathens and Pagans, ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Origen,</hi> were wont to celebrate the day of their birth and nativitie,<note place="margin">Orig. lib. 3. in Iob.</note> as onely louing this, and looking for none after this: but Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans muſt not ſo much celebrate and ſolemnize the day of their birth as of their death; becauſe albeit they looſe this life, yet they muſt looke for, and more loue another life. And the dying out of this world is not a death, but a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:8424:8"/>
life rather, <hi>Quia non moriuntur ſiqui mori videntur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Orig. vt ſupr</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they, ſaith the ſame S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Origen,</hi> who here ſeeme to die, doe not die indeed; for albeit they ſeeme to fleſh and blood to die, yet in truth and indeed they liue eternally. And as <hi>Iacob</hi> after his wreſtling with the Angel was ſinew ſhrunke, and had his thigh out of ioint, and went halting; but had his name changed, and was no more called <hi>Iacob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 32.28.31</note> but <hi>Iſrael,</hi> becauſe hee <hi>prevailed with God</hi> and did ſee God: Semblably, the godly after they haue wreſtled with the Angell of death on their death-beds, may haue the ſinews of their bodies ſhru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k vp, &amp; al the parts &amp; me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers thereof out of ioint (for death indeed diſiointeth all) ſo that they are not able to go vpright, but are carried on mens ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders vnto their graues; yet the Angel of death in the end ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe, that they haue power with God, &amp; that God wil bleſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; <hi>giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a new name,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Revel. 2.17.</note> ſo that they ſhal no more be called <hi>Iacobs,</hi> mortal me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>ſupplanting</hi> one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther here on earth, but <hi>Iſraëls, prevailers with God,</hi> ſeers of God, and bleſſed Saints of God in the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. The godly then haue great cauſe to reioice, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult over death, ſaying, <hi>O Death, where is thy ſting?</hi> Thou maieſt indeed ſting our bodies vnto death; but thou haſte loſt thy great ſtring, thou canſt not now any more ſting our ſoules to death. O Tyrant, thou mayſt kill our bodies for a time, but thou canſt not kill our ſoules for ever. So that they may ſay with <hi>S. Bernard; O mors,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern. ſerm. 26 ſup. Cantic.</note> 
               <hi>ſtimulus tuus non eſt ſtimulus, ſed iubilus,</hi> O Death, thy ſting is no ſting vnto vs, but our jubilee, and <hi>crowne of reioicing:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 2.19</note> thou thinkeſt to ſend vs quicke vnto hell,<note place="margin">Greg. Nyſſen</note> but thou ſendeſt vs quickly to heaven; thou art as a midwife (as <hi>Gregorie Nyſſene</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth,) to helpe to bring vs out of the womb of this world
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:8424:9"/>
into a better world,<note place="margin">Pſal. 27.13.</note> and into <hi>the land of the living;</hi> thou art the ſhip, wherein we ſaile vnto the haven of our happy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, whilſt we are here almoſt drowned in the deluge of this miſerable and wretched life.<note place="margin">Gen. 5.29.</note> And therefore as <hi>Lamech</hi> called his ſonne <hi>Noah,</hi> becauſe he ſhould comfort him &amp; make all his labour and ſorrow to ceaſe and reſt: in like manner all iuſt and righteous men may call death their <hi>Noah,</hi> the ſonne of their reſt and comfort from all their labours and ſorrowes and ſickneſſes &amp; diſeaſes &amp; paines; for then all theſe things and all ſuch like miſeries ſhal bee done away, and ſhall never be againe. When <hi>Vrbicius</hi> Governour vnder the perſecuting Emperour <hi>Aurelius Verus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſeb. l 4 hiſt Eccleſ. cap. 16</note> would needs put <hi>Lucius</hi> to death for the profeſſion of Chriſtianitie, <hi>Lucius</hi> ſcorned him, ſaying, O wicked Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, wilt thou put me to death? thou doſt me a great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and a great kindneſſe, for thou ſendeſt me from the tyrannie of a cruell Lord and Governour <hi>ad bonum patre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; clementem Regem Deum,</hi> to a good Father &amp; a mercifull King, even God my Chriſt and my Lord. So when death that Tyrant, to whom every knee muſt bend, and bow at his preſence, threatneth Chriſtians, they may iuſtly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer him, as <hi>Lucius</hi> there did <hi>Vrbicius;</hi> O Tyrant, doſt thou threaten to kill vs? thou doſt vs a great kindneſſe; thou freeſt vs from the tyrannie of wicked men here on earth, and ſendeſt vs to a loving father and a mercifull Lord in the heavens: thou freeſt vs from the ſtinking priſon of this world, to ſend vs to ſweet and pleaſant palaces in the world to come. And that they may likewiſe ſay as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Baſil</hi> ſaid to <hi>Modeſtus</hi> Governour vnder <hi>Valens</hi> the Emperour,<note place="margin">Greg. Naz. in orat 30 in laudem Baſil.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he threate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d his death, <hi>mors mihi beneficij loco erit, quia cito me ad Deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mittit, cui vivo, &amp; ad quem propero;</hi> Oh wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:8424:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Death, thou art a great benefit, a great advantage vnto me, for thou ſends me quickly to God to whome I liue, and to whom I long to goe. And therefore <hi>O Death, where is thy ſting? O Graue where is thy victory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now (Beloued) leſt the ſtream of diſcourſe ſhould carrie me beyond the compaſſe of the time,<note place="margin">Application.</note> and I ſhould tire out both my weake ſpirits and your Chriſtian pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; I come briefly to ſome ſhort application, as the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent occaſion and your expectation requireth: that as I haue hither to ſpoken of death, ſo now I may ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing alſo of this dead ſubiect preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted here before your eies. And albeit it be too hard a matter for mee either by ſpeech or action ſufficiently to commend his excellent worth, all that I can ſay being farre too little, and no way anſwerable therevnto: yet becauſe,<note place="margin">Hermol. Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barus in epiſt ad Ioh. Picum Mirandul.</note> as <hi>Hermolaus</hi> ſaid of a great learned man. <hi>Quia talem non laudat, propriae exiſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioni detrahit,</hi> ſo may I ſay of him, that if J ſhould not ſomewhat honour him with iuſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation, I ſhould much wrong my ſelfe, and wrong you all; I beſeech you therefore lend me your favourable patience but a while, whilſt I ſpeake briefly of his <hi>Learning, Life,</hi> and <hi>Death.</hi> That ſo both I may faithfully repay ſome part of that I owe him, (for deſerved praiſe is <hi>tanquam aes alienum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. Naz. orat. 25. in laudem Gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goniae.</note> as due debt, ſaith <hi>Greg. Nazianzen,</hi> and is to be paid even to the dead) and others alſo thereby may bee the more inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to emulate, and follow his ſteppes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, as touching his <hi>Learning;</hi> ſuch was his skill in the tongues, and his multiplicitie of knowledge in all Arts &amp; Sciences both divine and humane,<note place="margin">Mantuan. in Epiſt. ad Ioh. Picum Miran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dul.</note> that as <hi>Baptiſta Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuanus</hi> ſpake of <hi>Picus Mirandula, in vno eode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> homine vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deri Hieronymum &amp; Auguſtinum revixiſſe;</hi> ſo it ſhould
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:8424:10"/>
ſeeme that both theſe learned Fathers did liue in him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.<note place="margin">Act. 18.24.</note> He was an <hi>Apollos, mightie in the Scriptures;</hi> hee was familiarly converſant amongſt the <hi>Fathers,</hi> and as a father amongſt them; and amongſt the <hi>Schoolemen tanquam Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphicus Doctor,</hi> at whoſe mouth, as at an oracle, men might be reſolued in matters of doubt. And therefore moſt worthy was he of that chiefe place of the <hi>Doctour of the Chaire in Divinitie,</hi> which hee with ſo great applauſe and approbation, I had almoſt ſaid admiration, ſo long (even about twentie yeares) bare amongſt vs: out of whoſe <hi>Schoole</hi> haue <hi>proceeded</hi> ſo manie light ſtarres of our Church,<note place="margin">Greg Naz. orat. 25. in laudem Gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goniae.</note> that as <hi>Greg. Nazianzen</hi> compared his father, ſo might this our Reverend <hi>Father</hi> be well compared to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham.</hi> For he was an Abraham indeed, <hi>Pater multorum filiorum,</hi> a father of many ſonnes, by ſcholaſticall creation of them in the higheſt degrees of Learning: and that I may ſpeake the more to his honour, and to the honour of our Mother the Vniverſitie, a great part of the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Biſhops of the Land were thus his ſonnes; whereof<note n="*" place="margin">The Arch-Biſhop of Canterbury, the Biſhop of London.</note> two at this daie very worthily ſit at the ſterne of our Church, and are chiefe pillars thereof. But I will ſay no more of his learning, leſt my praiſe ſhould but eclipſe his fame, who was ſo much renowned for his preaching, rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding, diſputing, moderating, that all mouthes commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him, and ſtrangers admired him; ſo that his fame was ſpread abroad, and that in forraine countries as well as at home: and therefore it were ſore to be lamented, were it not that the good pleaſure of Almightie God was ſuch, that ſo much learning ſhould goe to the graue, and bee buried in the bowels of the earth.</p>
            <p>And ſo I haſten to ſpeake of his <hi>Life;</hi> which was ſo an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:8424:10"/>
to his learning, that it is hard to ſay which was more commendable and admirable to him, the one or the other; his Learning, or his life: they did both ſo equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meet and kiſſe each other in him. And ſurely, they are an happy couple where they meet together;<note place="margin">Plin. lib. 2. Nat. Hiſt. cap. 37.</note> 
               <hi>Geminae ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tares,</hi> like <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux:</hi> when they both appeare to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, they portend much good, and betoken a happy arrivall in heauen. He had as well taſted of the <hi>tree of life,</hi> I meane of good liuing in the world, as of the <hi>tree of know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge.</hi> Hee was not like thoſe of whom <hi>Seneca</hi> ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Sen. Ep. 95. ad Lucil.</note> 
               <hi>Qui poſtquam docti prodierunt, boni eſſe deſierunt; qui<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putare norunt, non vivere,</hi> who after they became learned began then to leaue of to doe well. Neither was hee like thoſe of whom <hi>Alvarus</hi> complaineth,<note place="margin">Alvarus lib. 2. Artic. 74.</note> who had rather <hi>apparentem, quam exiſtentem ſcientiam;</hi> rather an apparent &amp; ſeeming knowledge vnto the world, thereby to clime to riches, and promotions, and honours here on earth, then <hi>ſcientiam donum Spiritus ſancti,</hi> true and ſanctified knowledge which is the gift of the holy Ghoſt, whereby they might climbe vp to the kingdome of heaven. But he had otherwiſe and farre better learned Chriſt then ſo: &amp; was ſo holy, and vpright, and ſanctified in his life and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, that, as <hi>Alexander de Ales</hi> (as <hi>Trithemius</hi> repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth) was wont to ſay of <hi>Bonaventure,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Trithemius.</note> 
               <hi>quòd in eo non vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur Adam peccaſſe,</hi> that it did ſcarſe ſeeme that <hi>Adam</hi> had ſinned in him; ſo it might in ſome ſort be ſaid of him alſo in the very like manner, at leaſt in compariſon of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in this wicked generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſo ſpotleſſe was he &amp; blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe from all great enormous and ſcandalous offences: being full of the workes of the Spirit, as loue, peace, gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſſe, meekeneſſe temperance; full of tender mercy &amp;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:8424:11"/>
brotherly compaſſion; full of almes deeds and merciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vnto the poore. So that as hee was a ſhining bright lamp for his learning &amp; lightning others vnto the know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge of the truth: ſo was hee a ſhining bright ſtarre too in his life, enlightning others in the pathway to heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. He was <hi>praeco veritatis,</hi> a preacher of the truth; and hee was <hi>factor veritatis,</hi> a doer of the truth, he was an earneſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſour of the Orthodoxe faith, zealous of true religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; &amp; did hate with a perfect hatred al Idolatry, and ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; falſe religion.<note place="margin">The relation of the fellows</note> His common farewel to the Fellowes of his College, when he tooke any longer iourney was this <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendo vos dilectioni Dei, &amp; odio Papatus &amp; ſuperſtitionis,</hi> I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend you to the loue of God &amp; to the hatred of all Popery and ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And as he was a great Champio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the defence and maintenance of true Religion, ſo of al pietie and godlineſſe,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.</note> having on <hi>the whole armour of God:</hi> for as he had <hi>the ſhield of faith,</hi> ſo hee had <hi>the breſtplate of righteouſneſse;</hi> and as he had <hi>his loynes girt with veritie,</hi> and with <hi>the ſword of the ſpirit, which is the word of God,</hi> ſo hath he now <hi>the helmet of ſalvation,</hi> which is ſet on his head as a Diademe and Crowne of glorie in the heavens. He was meeke and humble as <hi>Moſes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 34.29.</note> and as <hi>Moſes wiſt not that the skinne of his face ſhone bright,</hi> which the children of Iſraël ſaw and admired; no more did he ſee and know how his knowledge and vertues did ſhine vnto the world, but was meeke and lowly in his owne eies.</p>
            <p>I wil not preſume too much of your patience to ſpeak any further of his life, albeit I verily aſſure my ſelfe you woulde thinke nothing too much and too long which ſhould be ſpoken of him: and for my ſelfe I could not wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t matter of diſcourſe in ſo worthy a ſubiect. Wherefore
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:8424:11"/>
conſidering howe much time hath beene already ſpent in the ſolemnizing of his funerals, I am willing to yeeld vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the time, and to mine owne and others weakneſſe; and and therefore haſtening to an end, I come in a word or two to ſpeake of his end and <hi>Death,</hi> leaving the manner &amp; circumſtances of his ſicknes, &amp; the name and nature of his diſeaſe, which is vnto me altogither vnknowne, and no more then conjectural with Phyſitions; arte &amp; the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of man being vnable to comprehend all that infinit variety of particuler diſeaſes, whereby God at his good pleaſure bringeth men vnto their ends. Now what ende and death can be iudged of him, but a good end, &amp; a good death? For a good life is the forerunner of a good death, according as <hi>S. Hierome</hi> ſaith, <hi>I haue not read or heard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hieronym.</note> 
               <hi>but that he who lived well, died well.</hi> And as the whole time of his ſickneſſe was accompanied with holy Praiers and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout meditations, ſo towards his end eſpecially he did e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſeeme to <hi>powre out his ſoule in praier;</hi> breathing out (as his ſhort breath would giue him leaue) theſe &amp; ſuch like heavenly ſongs, a little before day the ſame morning that he died, <hi>Come, oh come Lord Ieſus the bright morning ſtarre; Come Lord Ieſus; I deſire to be diſsolved, and to be with thee:</hi> as, if he had fully conquered death, and had ſaide in his ſoule, <hi>O Death, where is thy ſting? O Graue? Where is thy Victory? The Lord hath given me victorie over you through his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> And ſo when his voice began to faile him, that hee could pray no longer with his tongue, lifting vp his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds vnto heaven,<note place="margin">Pſal. 121.1.</note> and his <hi>eies vnto the hils from whence commeth ſalvation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 34 5.</note> he ſhortly after died a moſt ſweete and a quiet death: like vnto <hi>Moſes,</hi> who died <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>by the mouth of the Lord;</hi> that is, as ſome of the Rabbines &amp; Hebrew Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:8424:12"/>
interpret it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>with a kiſſe of Gods mouth:</hi> for ſo indeed death is to the godly ſweet as a kiſſe:<note place="margin">Rabbi Iſaak n Deut. 34.</note> &amp; therfore when they are ready to commend their ſoules vnto God, they may ſay with the Spowſe in the Canticles,<note place="margin">Cant. 1.1.</note> 
               <hi>Oſculetur me oſculo oris ſui,</hi> Let him kiſſe me with the kiſſes of his mouth. And thus this reverend man hath left vs, and hath left the worlde; and ſurely hee had little cauſe to loue the world, and it ſhould ſeeme the world did as litle loue him: ſo that as it was ſaid of <hi>Othniel,</hi> a good Iudge in Iſrael, that he died,<note place="margin">Gloſſa in Iud. cap. 3.</note> 
               <hi>quia indignus erat populus habere talem iudicem,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the people were not worthy to haue ſuch a Iudge; the like may be ſaid of him, <hi>Hollandus mortuus eſt, quia mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus indignus erat habere talem virum;</hi> I name him for loue &amp; honours ſake, HOLLAND is dead, becauſe the world was not worthy of him: for it did not reward him according to his worth; but the greater is his reward with the Lord to whom he is gone. Now the Lord graunt vs grace to liue all our daies in his feare, that at length we may die in his favour, and receiue the reward of everlaſting life. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:8424:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
